Guide to the Walter Mischel Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Walter Mischel papers
circa 1959-1984
SC0307
Mischel, Walter.
11 Linear feet
Correspondence, drafts of articles and chapters, speeches, lectures and teaching materials; audio tapes (reel-to-reel) of lectures.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Walter Mischel, 1984.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of psychology at Stanford University, 1962-1984, following teaching appointments at the University of Colorado and Harvard University. A fellow of the American Psychological Association, Mischel received the Distinguished Scientific Contribution award from the Association for outstanding contributions to personality theory and assessment in 1982.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, drafts of articles and chapters, speeches, lectures and teaching materials; audio tapes (reel-to-reel) of lectures.
Access Terms
Mischel, Walter.; Stanford University. Department of Psychology. Faculty.; Lectures.; Manuscripts (for publication).; Personality Assessment.; Psychology.
Collection Contents
- Papers, ACCN 1984-014
  Box 1-4 are articles & speeches, primarily in draft form
  - "Alternatives in the Pursuit of the Predictability and Consistency of Persons: Stable Data that Yield Unstable Interpretations," ca. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Consistency in Social Behavior" – grant application, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Development of Knowledge about Self Control," (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Delay of Gratification as Process and as Person Variable in Development" ca. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Interaction of Persons and Situations" 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Metacognition and the Rules of Delay" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "On the Interface of Cognition and Personality: Beyond the Person-Situation Debate" 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "On the Predictability of Behavior and the Structure of Personality" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Social Knowledge: Structure, Content, Use and Abuse," with letter from Nancy Cantor (co-author) 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Some Facets of Consistency: Replies to Epstein, Funder, and Bem" 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Funder, David C. "The 'Consistence' Controversy and the Accuracy of Personality Judgments" 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [loose and stray pages of articles, figures, etc.] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [correspondence] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - assorted Mischel reprints (Box 1)
  - "Beyond Déjà Vu in the Search for Cross-situational Consistency" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Convergences and Challenges in the Search for the Person," APA address 1983 – draft 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Convergences and Challenges in the Search for the Person," APA address 1983 – drafts July 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Convergences and Challenges in the Search for the Person," APA address 1983 – drafts August 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Facets of Consistency: Replies to Epstein, Funder, and Bem" – drafts June 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Facets of Consistency: Replies to Epstein, Funder, and Bem" – miscellaneous pages (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Symposium on Interactional Psychology, Sweden 1975 – miscellaneous information (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mellstrom, Martin, "General Versus Specific Trait Anxiety Measures in the Prediction of Fear of Snakes, Heights, and Darkness" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - [loose and stray pages of articles, figures, etc.] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "A Cognitive Social Learning Approach to Morality and Self-regulation," ca. 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "A Cognitive Social Learning View of Person X Situation Interaction," paper presented at APA symposium 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Effective Plans for Self-Control in Children" 1976 and 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "George Kelly's Anticipation of Psychology: A Personal Tribute" (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Language and Social Cognition: Verbal Communicators are Trait Theorists" (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "The Nature and Consistency of Self-Control" (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "On the Predictability and Structure of Behavior" (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Personality and Assessment, chapter 5 – draft (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Personality and Assessment, chapter 6 – draft (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Personality and Assessment – reviews and correspondence re, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Prototypes in Person Perception" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Prototypicality and Personality: Effects on Free Recall and Personality Impressions" (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "On the Role of Ideation in Voluntary Delay for Symbolically-Presented Rewards" (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Social Competence and Depression: The Role of Illusory Self-Perceptions" (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Specificity Theory and the Construction of Personality," based on APA address, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mischel, Harriet, "Trust and Delay of Gratification," Ph.D. thesis, Radcliffe, 1963 (2 typescript copies) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - [loose and stray pages of articles, figures, etc.] (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - one reprint (Box 3)
  - items to compare to existing copies in boxes 1-2 (Box 3)
  - "An argument for the existence of a relationship between activity preferences and change in social behavior" – outline, illustrations, charts (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Chapter 19 Social Influence" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Chapter 20 Social Cognition and Interaction" (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "A Cognitive Social Learning Approach to Assessment" (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Further Studies on Symbolic Reward Presentation," 5/16/73 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Predicting Achievement Behavior" – possible notes or corrections (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "The Role of Cues in Plans for Children's Self-Control," 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "III Self-Encoding" (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Self-Regulatory Processes" 1979-80: grant proposal (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Studying Desegregation: A Cognitive Social Learning View" 1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Toward a Comprehensive Theory of Personality and Behavior Organization" 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - items to compare to existing copies in boxes 1-2 [comprises nearly half of this box 4] (Box 4)
    [Subsequent boxes have not yet been listed (as of 8/9/05) but are also labeled as containing articles and speeches.]
- ACCN 1984-018
  - Audio tapes (reels)
    [The following 16 tapes appear to have been first used for 1958-60 talks by other people but were reused to record Mischel's talks in 1972; most of the labeling on the edge reflects the earlier usage.]
    - [Berman 4/30/59 and 5/8/59;] Personality – W. Mischel, 5/15/72 (Box 1)
    - [Berman, 6/9/59;] Personality – W. Mischel, 4/5/72 (Box 1)
    - [Harrison 6/1/59;] Mischel 5/8/72 (Box 1)
    - Mischel, Psych 134, 5/22/72 [also labeled Bergin 1958] (Box 1)
    - [Harrison 1959;] Personality, Mischel, 5/3/72 (Box 1)
    - Blank tape [labeled Bergin-Sherman 1959] (Box 1)
    - Bergin July 1958 (side 2); Mischel 5/17/72 (Box 1)
    - Personality, W. Mischel, 5/24/72 (Box 1)
    - Personality, W. Michel, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Personality, W. Michel, 4/26/72 (Box 1)
    - Personality, W. Michel, 4/3/72 (Box 1)
    - Personality, W. Michel, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Personality, W. Michel, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Walter's lecture, side 1, May 7, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Side 1, May 10 (Box 1)
    - 26081 (Box 1)
  - Other tapes, also reels; speaker is presumed to be Walter Mischel, except where noted:
    - Dr. Lewis Goldberg on The Uses of Traits: a Defense. UC Santa Barbara, Nov. 21, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Eliot Aronson, May 21, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Side 1, April 16, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Side 1: April 12, 1971 (Little Hans) tape broke for last 10-15 min. (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled tape (Box 1)
    - May 17, 1971 Side 1 (Box 1)
    - Existing label blacked out; no new information (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled tape, but with faint marking on front "5-24 probably" (Box 1)
    - April 26, 1971 – side 1 (Box 1)
    - April 30, 1971, Side 1 (Kelly) (Box 1)
  - Transcripts of Mischel's taped lectures on personality
    - Lecture 4/26/71 (normal and abnormal personality) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lecture 4/30/71 (George Kelly's theory on personal constructs) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lecture 5/7/71 (conclusion on George Kelly) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lecture 5/10/71 (psychotic behavior) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lecture 5/14/71 (schizophrenic reactions) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lecture 5/17/71 (schizophrenic reactions) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lecture by Eliot Aronson 5/21/71 (encounter groups) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lecture 5/24/71 (response to Aronson and treatment from a behavioral point of view (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lecture 5/28/71 (behavioral treatment options) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Attention in Delay of Gratification," ca. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Cognition in Self-Imposed Delay of Gratification" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Cognitive Appraisals and Transformations in Self-Control" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Determinants of Selective Memory about the Self," 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Direct versus Indirect Personality Assessment: Evidence and Implications," 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Effects of Attention to Symbolically-presented Rewards upon Self-control" (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Effects of Expected Delay Time on the Subjective Value of Rewards and Punishments," ca. 1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Effects of Purpose on the Organization and Recall of Information in Person Perception," 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Effects of Success and Failure on Self-Gratification" (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "The Layman's Use of Trait and Behavioral Information to Predict Behavior," 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Role of Knowledge and Ideation in the Development of Delay Capacity," 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Selective Attention to the Self: Situational and Dispositional Determinants" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Self-Control and the Self," 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Sex typing and Socialization" draft for a chapter in Mussen (ed.), Manual of Child Psychology, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Stanford University, Dept. of Psychology, miscellaneous memos (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Grant: Psychology-Personality and Psychopathology, 1978-81 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Grant: Psychology-Personality and Psychopathology, 1975-77 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Grant: Psychology-Personality and Psychopathology, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Grant: Psychology-Personality and Psychopathology, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Grant: Psychology-Personality and Psychopathology, 1966-71 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Chapter 5, Utility (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Chapter 6, Principles of Social Behavior (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Chapter 7, Behavior Change (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Chapter 8, Assessment for Behavior Change (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Chapter 9, Behavioral Stability and Prediction (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - References (for Personality and Assessment?) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Item to compare to Box 3 in earlier accession (Box 2)
    - Galleys for Personality and Assessment (Box 2)